<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Exochē tou Christou, Christ's preeminence in a question propounded, discussed, &amp; resolved, that Christ was the first, that with flesh and blood entred into the kingdome of heaven / by Nicholas Gawen.</title>
            <author>Gawen, Nicholas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G395</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23944</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07933130</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07933130</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40509</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42520)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40509)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1207:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Exochē tou Christou, Christ's preeminence in a question propounded, discussed, &amp; resolved, that Christ was the first, that with flesh and blood entred into the kingdome of heaven / by Nicholas Gawen.</title>
                  <author>Gawen, Nicholas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Primacy.</term>
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Ascension.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40509:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40509:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. CHRIST'S PREEMINENCE; In a Queſtion Propounded, Diſcuſſed, &amp; Reſolved; That Chriſt was the firſt, that with Fleſh, and Blood entred into the Kingdome of Heaven.</p>
            <p>By NICOLAS GAVVEN Miniſter, and Preacher of the Word of God at <hi>Biſter</hi> in the County of <hi>OXFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Who being the brightneſſe of his (Father's) glory, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Image of his perſon: and upholding all things by the word of his power, when he had by himſelf purged our ſins, ſate down on the right hand of the Majeſtie on High.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 1.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>That in all things he might have the preeminence.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Coloſ: 1.18.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by <hi>H: Hall</hi> Printer to the Univerſity. 1668.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40509:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40509:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipfull D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> LAMPLUGH D. D. Archdeacon of <hi>Midleſex,</hi> and Principall of <hi>Albane</hi> Hall in <hi>Oxford,</hi> Grace on Earth, and Glory in Heaven.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot to make too wide <hi>Gates</hi> to my little <hi>Myndus;</hi> leſt <hi>ſome rayling Zoylus, carping Momus, barking Diogenes, criticall, and cenſorious Ariſtarchus,</hi> having eies more quick, and piercing then <hi>Lynceus,</hi> the <hi>Eagle, Crocodile,</hi> or <hi>Epidaurian ſerpent;</hi> ſhould except, and maunder at this my poore innocent, and firſt borne infant; that it was of monſtrous, and deformed ſhape: much like to <hi>Martial</hi>'s monſter, having the daring, and outfacing head of <hi>Hector,</hi> but the ſpiny, puny ſpider legs of <hi>Aſtianax;</hi> or juſt like to a child ſick of the rickets, whoſe head ſwels, and growes too big for the body: I eſteem, and reckon it my bounden duty, to give your Worſhip an account of two things: Firſt concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the occaſion of my writing this Treatiſe: Secondly
<pb facs="tcp:40509:3"/>concerning the cauſe of the Dedication.</p>
            <p>The occaſion was this: Being at a certain time in company with one of my Pariſhioners; he by chance, <hi>pro more, &amp; amore, inter diſcumbendum, inter diſcurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> put the queſtion to me; whether or no, Chriſt was the firſt that <hi>with fleſh and blood,</hi> entred into the Kingdone of Heaven. To which queſtion I anſwered Affirmatively; yea, and fortified my Anſwer, for the time preſent, with ſome poſitive Texts, and Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Scripture: but ſo it was, that upon that mean occaſion, I could find no reſt in my thoughts, till I had given way, and ſcope to my meditations, to dilate, and enlarge themſelves, and take a contemplative ramble, and vagary, thorough the ſpacious, and pleaſant fields of the ſacred Scriptures; there to diſcover, and gather what flowers I could, for the making up of this my mean garland, or rather poſie; and the enlergement and improvement of my former Anſwer.</p>
            <p>And that, that prov'd another ſpur to me, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take this Taske, was for that no man, as ever I heard or read of, purpoſely, <hi>&amp; ex induſtriâ</hi> traced this ground, and undertook this Argument before me: why you'l ſay? becauſe no man yet e're doubted of the truth of the aſſertion. But this objection is much to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: becauſe as there wanted not ſome who endeavoured to rob our Saviour of the prerogative of his Divinitie: as <hi>Carpocrates, Cerinthus, Ebion, Theodoſian, Photinus, Arius, that Arrant Heretique;</hi> who pretended, that he had 42. Texts of Scripture to prove that Chriſt was not true and perfect God. And as there have not wanted
<pb facs="tcp:40509:3"/>others who have attempted to diſpoile, and rob him of his Humanitie, as <hi>Marcian of Pontus, Saturninus of Antioch, Baſilides, Valentinus, Apelles with his minion Philumela, Apollinares,</hi> and others. And as there hath not been wanting others; who have attempted to rob him of the integrity, and ſingularity of his perſon, as <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> who did <hi>Dichotomize,</hi> cut him aſunder, and make two Chriſts of him; the one <hi>Divine,</hi> the other <hi>Humane:</hi> ſo queſtionleſſe there have not wanted ſome who have atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted to deprive him of this <hi>Preeminence</hi> of his humanity; of its firſt aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; entrance into heaven; let <hi>Marcion</hi> ſtand for inſtance, who taught that Chriſt had but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the meer reſemblance &amp; appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition of man; &amp; <hi>Eutiches</hi> too, who affirmed that Chriſt's Humanitie was quite <hi>Abſorpt,</hi> ſwallowed up, and annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by his Divinity, and ſo deprived of all bodily aſcent, &amp; conſequently of the firſt aſcent into Heaven.</p>
            <p>But no true believer, you'l ſay, ever doubted hereof. Anſw: Though it may be granted, that the better, and moſt learned ſort of believers, whom the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb:</hi> 5.12. termes <hi>men of full age, who by reaſon of uſe, have their ſenſes exerciſed to diſcern both good, and evill:</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doubted hereof, yet it is to be feared; that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettered ſort, and thoſe endowed with mean knowledge have doubted thereof, or not firmly, and ſedledly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved it, witneſſe the queſtion put to mee that muſt needs proceed from doubting or unbelief thereof.</p>
            <p>But be it granted, that none yet ever doubted of our Saviours firſt bodily aſcent into Heaven, yet this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, for the proofe and confirmation thereof is not (eſpecially in theſe times) unſeaſonable, unneceſſary:
<pb facs="tcp:40509:4"/>and that <hi>Phyſitian</hi> is not to be blamed, that gives an <hi>Antidote</hi> as well for the prevention, as the removall of a diſeaſe. and ſuch is the counter-poſition of this Theſis; a botch, a bile, a diſeaſe in the Church, if it happen to be entertained, and take place, and quite contrary to ſound Doctrine. They that hold that any man before Chriſt bodily aſcended into Heaven, do in a manner, and after a ſort Un-Chriſt our Saviour, which thus I prove:</p>
            <p>They that rob, and deprive Chriſt of All, or Any of his Offices, do in a manner un-Chriſt him, for from his unction, and inauguration into his Offices, of <hi>King,</hi> of <hi>Prieſt,</hi> of <hi>Prophet:</hi> he hath the title, or denomination of <hi>Meſsias,</hi> or <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that man that holds, that any man before Chriſt, bodily aſcended into Heaven, doth as much as in him lies, ſtrip, and rob Chriſt of his office of <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> of being our High Prieſt, it being proper, and peculiar to his Prieſthood, to enter firſt into the <hi>holy place: viz:</hi> the Kingdom of heaven, <hi>There to make interceſsion for us.</hi> As the High Prieſt of the Leviticall Law, firſt of all, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of all, after he had ended his Sacrifice without, entred with the blood thereof within <hi>the vail, to ſprinkle it before the Mercie ſeat,</hi> and to make interceſſion for the people, whereas the <hi>people ſtood without; Luk:</hi> 1.10. As the Apoſtle plainly teacheth, <hi>Heb:</hi> 9. <hi>v</hi> 7, 11, 12. by a compariſon between Chriſt, and the High Prieſt of the Levitical Law; and therefore I conclude, that they that hold, that any man before Chriſt, bodily aſcended into Heaven, do in a manner, and after a for Un-Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:40509:4"/>our Saviour, and ſo grate upon the foundation. The Theſis therefore that I have fortified, in this Diſcourſe may be received without fear; refuſed it cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger. I am perſwaded that this my Infant, as it is an Infant, and ſpeakes like an Infant; ſo will it behave it ſelf as an Infant in the world; that is innocently; if it can do no good, I am confident it will do no wrong.</p>
            <p>This my poore Tractate ſuch as it is, whether blind, or lame, or maimed, or withered, or any, or every way defective, do I preſume to preſent, and dedicate to your worſhip, but why and wherefore, which is the ſecond thing whereof I am to render an account. No other cauſe, ſcope, end, or fetch have I, but your innate vertue, goodneſſe, kindneſſe, courteſie poliſhed, and embeliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by grace, celebrated in the months of All in general, and experienc'd by my ſelf in particular, drawing mee with a kind, of magnetical vertue, inviting, and citing mee.</p>
            <p>It is obſerved by a learned, and grave Divine of our Church, that God hath depictured, and characterized, thoſe refulgent, and eminent vertues, and graces, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he endued ſome men in their names. The golden eloquence of <hi>Chriſoſtome;</hi> the milkie vein of <hi>Lactantius,</hi> the immortall fame of <hi>Athanaſius, that grand Ariano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtix;</hi> the golden wit, &amp; moſt great, &amp; profound judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Aurelius Auguſtinus;</hi> the peaceable diſpoſition of <hi>Irenaeus;</hi> the Divine fruitfulneſs of <hi>Policarpus,</hi> are inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated in the names: the ſame lot hath befaln you, <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bei Lampadis inſtar;</hi> for what is <hi>Lamplough,</hi> but as if it ſhould be ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: as having your name deriv'd from a Lamp; thereby to
<pb facs="tcp:40509:5"/>intimate, that like the Baptiſt, you are a <hi>burning light</hi> in your life and converſation. Sir, I flatter you not; flattery is a bribe, that I am as unable to give, as you to receive, I give you no more then your due; and all that know you will moſt willingly afford you ſo much.</p>
            <p>The bare, and naked conſideration of this your goodneſſe, both by nature and grace, hath ſtrongly, and irreſiſtibly importun'd mee, and prevail'd over mee; and kindled, and enflamed my affection, and deſire, and made it to burne (like thoſe ancient Olibian fires, which An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie (as I remember) dedicated to the remembrance of their deceaſed Hero's, and Benefactors) with zeal to ſerve you conſtantly, &amp; perpetually, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Homer,</hi> till death us do part, and in expreſſion thereof to dedicate to you this poor Pamphlet, which I intreat you to accept: this is both the profeſſion, and proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion together with the ſubſcription of him who is</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your Worſhips moſt hamble ſervant to ſerve you in what he may in the Lord <hi>NICOLAS GAVVEN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40509:5"/>
            <head>Chriſt's Preeminence.</head>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt Argument that I take to confirm my Poſition, I draw, and take <hi>à Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latis, &amp; ab utriuſque contrariis effectibus, &amp; operationibus,</hi> that is to ſay, from an Analogie, and compariſon taken from the firſt, and ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and their contrary effects, workings, and operations. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>By one man ſin entred into the world, and death by by ſin:</hi> not only death temporal, but alſo death eternal; And in this death eternal you muſt obſerve, that there is a twofold formality, and denomination. For it is not only (as the Schoolmen ſpeak) a puniſhment po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive of ſenſe, and of ſenſible Anguiſh, Smart, and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but likewiſe a puniſhment privative, and of the loſſe of infinite, and eternal joy, comfort, and content; It is not only incluſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, an incarceration, incluſion, and ſhutting into Hell, but it is likewiſe <hi>excluſio,</hi> an exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſhutting, and bolting out of Heaven. So that when <hi>Adam</hi> ſin'd againſt his Maker, and by ſin fell from his original integritie, and perfection, he by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40509:6"/>his fall became not only the heir of Hell, but alſo the <hi>Bandido,</hi> and exile of Heaven, and that not only in his own behalfe, but likewiſe in the behalfe of all his children, and poſterity, (who were to ſtand, or fall in Him) and that for evermore.</p>
            <p>And this very thing was Typified immediately after the fall of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> by the Lord's chaſing, driving, and excluding of him, for his ſin out of terreſtrial Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.24. <hi>The Lord drave out the man, and placed at the Eaſt of the garden of Eden, Cherubins, and a flaming ſword, which turned every way, to keep the tree of life.</hi> In this narration there is no doubt to be made, but that the Terreſtrial Paradiſe, did Typifie, and ſhadow out unto us, the Coeleſtial; the beauty of the place, the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, variety, and excellency of the fruits thereof; the incomparable, and unconceivable refreſhments, joyes, delights, and pleaſures of the Kingdome of God; <hi>In whoſe preſence is the fulneſs of joy, and at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for evermore. Pſal.</hi> 16.11. God's friendly, and familiar walking, and talking with <hi>Adam</hi> (during his continuance in his perfect eſtate) in earthly Paradiſe; That immediate, and Soul-gladding communion, and fellowſhip, that God vouchſafeth his Saints; and <hi>the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, in the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Heb.</hi> 12.23. The tree of life doubtleſs ſignified, our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, as Saint <hi>John</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 22.2. the driving of <hi>Adam</hi> out of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, the excluſion and ſhutting of himſelfe, and all his poſterity out of Heaven; God placing at the Eaſt-end of the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> Cherubims, and a flaming ſword, which turned every way, to keep the way of the tree of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40509:6"/>life; the ſtepping, and coming in of God's fiery law, given (as the Apoſtle ſaith) by the Angels on mount Sinai, <hi>which is ſharper then a two-edged ſword, piercing, even to the dividing aſunder of ſoule, and ſpirit, and of the joynts, and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts and intents of the Heart.</hi> And ſo like the flaming ſword at Edens gate, turning every way, this way, and that way, meeting with every the leaſt perceptible thought and contrivance of the heart, either as a right rule to meaſure it, or as a juſt Judge to condemne it, thereby to ſtop, and bar man out, from entring into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, and eternal life; by reaſon of an utter impotencie, and impoſſibilitie, that (immediately upon his fall) befell <hi>Adam,</hi> and all his poſteritie for ever to performe, and fulfill it: The ſumme of this firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be given in theſe few words.</p>
            <p>The effects, workings, and operations of the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> (though directly contrary, yet) are correſpondent, and anſwerable to the working, operations, and effects of the ſecond, as the Apoſtle ſhewes, by divers branches, and members of compariſon. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. For which cauſe he calls the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> the figure of Chriſt which was to come, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14. I adde ſecondly.</p>
            <p>But the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> being the firſt that ſinned, was firſt perſonally himſelfe; ſecondly, repreſentatively, in reſpect of all his poſterity, thruſt literally out of earthly; myſtically, and ſymbolically, out of the Heavenly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe: therefore I conclude, that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> being the firſt man, and only man, that fulfille all righteouſneſs, in the behalf of his elect, was likewiſe the firſt man that opened the gate of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40509:7"/>Heaven, <hi>entred into that within the vail; Heb.</hi> 6.19. And took poſſeſſion of the Kingdome of Heaven, in the behalfe of all his elect, according to that golden expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Church; in that Hymne, or Song, (whether compiled by <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> or <hi>Auſtin,</hi> or both, it matters not) <hi>When thou hadſt overcome the ſharpneſſe of death, thou diaſt open the Kingdome of Heaven to all believers:</hi> And this is the reaſon, that the Apoſtle calls Chriſt <hi>our fore-runner, which for us is entred into that within the vail, Heb.</hi> 6.20. And Chriſt (a little before his paſſion, Reſurrection, and Aſcention) told his diſciples, that <hi>he went to prepare a place for them. Joh.</hi> 14.20.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2:</label> A ſecond Argument I draw from thoſe words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20, where he calls Chriſt, <hi>the firſt fruits of thoſe that ſlept: But now is Chriſt riſen from the dead, and become the firſt fruits of them that ſleep:</hi> In which words the Apoſtle aſſures us of three things: Firſt, that Chriſt is riſen from the dead, of that there is no doubt. Secondly, that he is firſt riſen from the dead. Thirdly, that the reſurrection of Chriſt the head, is the ſure pledge, and in fallible earneſt, of the reſurrection of all his members: for which cauſe he calls him the firſt fruits of thoſe that ſlept, underſtand thoſe latter words onely of all true believers; for here the Apoſtle allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the firſt fruits of the earth, that the people did offer unto the Lord in the time of the Leviticall Law, which were bleſſed, and priviledged with a double pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, and qualification: Firſt, Of preſentation, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, of Sanctification: firſt to be offer'd of all other, ſecondly to ſacrifice all the other fruits of the Harveſt. Chriſt, I ſay, is the firſt fruits of all believers in two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects,</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40509:7"/>
            <p>Firſt, in reſpect of his reſurrection, for that he is the firſt, that ever perfecty, and fully roſe from the dead, as the firſt fruits, (as I conceive,) were thoſe that were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt, and ſooneſt ripe; for <hi>is eſt primus, ante quem nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus;</hi> He muſt needs be the firſt in order, before whom there is not another, ſaith <hi>Tertullian. li. de carne Chriſti.</hi> So ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.23. <hi>Chriſt is the firſt fruits, and after they that are Chriſts at his coming:</hi> In this reſpect the Apoſtle calls him, <hi>the firſt borne from the dead. Col.</hi> 1.18. <hi>And the firſt borne among many brethren. Rom.</hi> 8.29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If it be here objected, that <hi>Elias</hi> raiſed the widow of <hi>Zarephtha's</hi> ſon to life; and <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Suna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites ſon from the dead; And <hi>that his dead bones quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and raiſed a dead man that touched them, to life;</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 13.21. which cauſed the wiſe Syracides to give this encomium and applauſe of him; <hi>that after his death his body propheſied. Ecclus.</hi> 48.13. and therefore Chriſt was not the firſt that roſe from the dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As before (by way of occupation, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention) that Chriſt was the firſt, that fully, and perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly roſe from death to life; firſt becauſe he alone roſe by his own power; <hi>Having looſed the paines of death, for that it was impoſſible that he ſhould be holden of it,</hi> as ſaith Saint <hi>Peter, Act.</hi> 2.24. And <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. <hi>That Chriſt was declared to be the Son of God with power, according to the ſpirit of holineſs, by the reſurrection from the dead:</hi> whereas the former inſtanced examples did not. Secondly, for that he alone roſe victoriouſly, and triumphantly over the dead, as a man quite freed, and diſengaged from it, never againe to returne to it, nor to its bondage, and captivitie; ſo ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> of Chriſt's
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40509:8"/>conflict with death; <hi>He led Captivity Captive, Eph</hi> 4.8. And againe, <hi>Chriſt being raiſed from the dead, dieth no more, death hath no more Dominion over him. Rom:</hi> 6.9. And Chriſt himſelfe <hi>Apoc:</hi> 1.18. <hi>I am he that liveth, and was dead, and behold I live for evermore.</hi> Whereas the former parties, though they roſe from death to life, yet was it not to an immortal, but a mortal life; a life ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſtill to the bondage of corruption, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lyable to the law of death, to return again to the place from whence they came, <hi>viz:</hi> the dark chambers and receptacles of death, at the terme and end of life: as a priſoner may be ſpecial diſpenſation, part out of priſon for a while, having his keeper with him, to return, and bring him back thither again at pleaſure, and in due time. And this Doctrine is ſtrengthened with the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and ſuffrage of the Author that beares the name of <hi>Juſtine Martyr, Quaeſt. &amp; Reſponſ: ad Orthodoxos, quaeſt:</hi> 85. <hi>(Juſtine Martyr's</hi> worke it is not, as plainly appeares by the very next queſtion, wherein he cites <hi>Origen,</hi> that lived 80. yeares after him:) for thus he ſpeaketh very peremptorily <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. never was there any reſurrection of any man to an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal and incorruptible life, beſides our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, for which cauſe he is called, <hi>the firſt begotten of the dead, and the firſt fruits of thoſe that ſlept.</hi> And this is the firſt reaſon, or reſpect, why Chriſt is termed the firſt fruits; I ſay in reſpect of his Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, (which makes more to my purpoſe) Chriſt is called the firſt fruits, in reſpect of is Aſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and entrance into the Kingdome of Heaven, wherein he bears proportion, and directly anſwers to the firſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40509:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>fruits of the Levitical Law; for as the firſt fruits (as I conceive) were ſo called, not only, for that they were ſome of the rath-ripes of the Crop; <hi>Ex.</hi> 22.29. &amp; 23.19. (for of all living creatures alſo, every firſt borne, <hi>That which firſt opened the matrix, was holy unto the Lord: Exod:</hi> 13.2. &amp; 22.29.) but alſo for that they had the prerogative, and preeminence of preſentation, being firſt of all others preſented, and offered unto the Lord, in the Tabernacle, being both the repreſentation, and ſanctification of the whole crop: <hi>Rom:</hi> 11.16. So Chriſt likewiſe is the firſt fruits of all true beleevers; not only in reſpect of his reſurrection, <hi>being the firſt borne from the dead, Coloſ:</hi> 1.18. but alſo in reſpect of his Aſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and entrance into Heaven (Typified by the earthly Tabernacle,) whither <hi>as our Captain, Heb:</hi> 2.10. <hi>Surety, Heb:</hi> 7.22. <hi>Fore-runner, Heb:</hi> 6.20. He is entred <hi>to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the preſence of God for us, and to make interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to God for us, Heb:</hi> 9.24. <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.434. That ſo being <hi>made pertakers of his holineſs here, Heb:</hi> 12.10. we may be partakers of his glory herafter. This is that which Chriſt made interceſſion for to his Heavenly Father in our behalfe, whiles he was here on earth; <hi>Father I will, that they alſo whom thou haſt given mee, be with mee where I am, that they may behold my Glory Joh:</hi> 17.24. And this is no more then reaſon; that he who firſt, and alone roſe victoriouſly over death; ſhould firſt of all enter triumphantly into life, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 4.9, 10. <hi>He that Aſcended, what is it, but that he alſo deſcended firſt, into the lower parts of the earth? He that deſcended, is the ſame alſo that aſcended up far above all Heavens.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 8. the Apoſtle plainly proveth from <hi>Pſ:</hi> 68.18.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40509:9"/>That the ground, and cauſe that Chriſt firſt of all men, entred into Heaven, was for that he firſt of all men, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed over death, <hi>And led Captivity Captive;</hi> And no doubt to be made, but that the Pſalmiſt, by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of propheſie, pointed at the glorious reſurrection, and aſcention of Chriſt, when he ſaid, <hi>God is aſcended up on high, with a ſhout, the Lord with a ſound of a Trumpet. Pſal</hi> 47.5. The ſumme of this Argument may be given in theſe few words.</p>
            <p>That which befell the firſt fruits in relation to the earthly Tabernacle, befell Chriſt in relation to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly (for this cauſe the Apoſtle calls Chriſt the firſt fruits,) but the firſt fruits, of all other, were firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and offered, before the Lord in the Terreſtriall Tabernacle, therefore Chriſt of all men firſt entred, and appeared before the Lord in the Coeleſtiall.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>3</label> A third Argument may be taken from the Prieſthood of Chriſt, and the collation, and compariſon of Chriſt, with the High Prieſt of the Leviticall Law: Chriſt is the High Prieſt of all believers, ſo we believe, and ſo the Apoſtle teacheth us all along his golden Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi> Now as touching the properties, and duties of the High Prieſt, the Apoſtle plainly tells us, <hi>Heb:</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>That every high Prieſt taken from among men, is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for men, in things pertaining to God, that he may offer both gifts, and ſacrifices for ſins, who can have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion on the ignorant, and on them that are out of the way, for that he himſelfe alſo is compaſſed with infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which Text, the Apoſtle (as we may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bſerve) ſets down <hi>five proper Attributes of every-high Prieſt;</hi> all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40509:9"/>which i a moſt excellent meaſure, and after a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent manner are in our High Prieſts, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: 1. The High Prieſt was a man choſen from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, ſo is Chriſt the moſt perfect man that ever was. 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, He was to Act, and deale with God as an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in the behalf of men, ſo doth Chriſt: <hi>There is one Mediator betwixt God and man, the man Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.5. 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> He was to offer gifts, and ſacrifices to God for ſins, ſo doth Chriſt; and as the Apoſtle makes the compariſon, <hi>Heb:</hi> 9.13, 14. <hi>If the blood of buls and of goats, and the aſhes of an heifer ſprinkling the unclean, ſanctifieth to the purifying of the fleſh; how much more ſhall the blood of Chriſt, who thorough the eternal ſpirit, offered himſelf without ſpot to God, purge your conſciences from dead workes to ſerve the living God?</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> Every High Prieſt muſt be ſuch an one, that could have compaſſion on the ignorant, and on them that are out of the way. Such an one is Chriſt, <hi>Heb:</hi> 4.15. <hi>We have not an high Prieſt, which cannot be touched with the feeling of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, but was in all points tempted, like as we are, yet without ſin.</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, He muſt be lawfully called, and ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for no man taketh this honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was <hi>Aaron: So Chriſt</hi> (ſaith our Apoſtle) <hi>glorified not himſelf, to be made an high Prieſt, but he that ſaid unto him, Thou art my Son, to day have I begotten thee: as he ſaith alſo in another place; Thou art a Prieſt for ever after the order of Melchizedecb, Heb:</hi> 5.5.6.</p>
            <p>Now whereas the duties, and offices of the High Prieſt were many, and divers; as firſt to pray for the people. Secondly, to offer ſacrifice for ſins. Thirdly,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40509:10"/>to carry the blood of the beaſts that were ſacrificed into into the Holy place. And fourthly, and laſtly, there to make interceſſion for the people. Know and underſtand, that ſome of theſe offices he did fulfill and diſcharge, without the Sanctuary, and ſome within the Sanctuary; The offices which he did perform without the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry were two; firſt to pray for the people: Secondly, to offer Sacrifice for their ſins. The offices which he did performe within the Sanctuary were likwiſe two: Firſt, to take and carry the blood of the ſlain Sacrifice into the holy place, <hi>and ſprinkle it with his finger upon the mercy ſeat. Levit:</hi> 16 14. And ſecondly to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for the people. Even the like (for all the world) was done and performed by Jeſus Chriſt our High Prieſt, who was Typified, and prefigured by the High Prieſt of the Levitical Law; ſome parts of his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood he did, and performed on earth without the vail, without the Heavenly Sanctuary. Firſt as our High Prieſt he prayed for us, <hi>And in the daies of his fleſh offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up prayers, and ſupplications with ſtrong crying, and teares. Heb.</hi> 5.7. And <hi>Joh:</hi> 17. before his laſt Paſſeover, and paſſion; and likewiſe in the garden of <hi>Gethſemene;</hi> and upon the Croſſe before his death, and departure out of this world. 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, After this prayer for us, he offered up himſelfe a ſacrifice for us on the Croſſe, <hi>Chriſt our Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over is ſacrificed for us,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.7. which ſacrifice being once done, performed, and as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Finiſhed</hi> at his death, the third day did he riſe againe, aſcend, and enter into the moſt holy place, even the Heaven of Heavens, perpetually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſenting to his Holy, and Heavenly Father, the merit, and value of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40509:10"/>his owne blood, and bloody paſſion on our behalfe, and perpetually <hi>appearing in the ſight of God, and making interceſſion for us.</hi> The ſumme of this Argument may be rendred in theſe few words:</p>
            <p>There is an infallible, and undeniable Analogie, and Correſpondence betwixt the High Prieſt of the Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Law; and our Lord and dear Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, as the Apoſtle declareth at large in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> and ſpecially in the 5, 7, 8, 9. Chapters. But the High Prieſt of the Levitical Law only, and but once a year; firſt of all, and inſteed of all, after he had ended his Sacrifice without, entred with the blood thereof, <hi>within the vaile, to ſprinkle it before the Mercy-ſeat, and to make Interceſſion, and Attonement for the people, Exod.</hi> 30.10. <hi>whereas the people ſtood without, Luk:</hi> 1.10. And therefore I conclude, That our High Prieſt, our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, after he had once finiſhed his bitter, and bloody paſſion, and death here on earth, roſe againe, aſcended up on high, and firſt of all, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of all his elect, in his Humane body, intred into Heaven, to preſent the merit of his death and paſſion to his Heavenly Father in our behalfe, and as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb:</hi> 1.3. <hi>Sate down at the right hand of the Majeſty on high, there perpetually to make interceſsion for them, Rom:</hi> 8.34. and <hi>Heb:</hi> 7.25. And this well agreeth with that ancient, and excellent ſaying of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Commentary on the 39. Pſalme, where he ſaith what is ſo proper to Chriſt, as to ſtand by God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for an Advocate for the people? And that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> likewiſe pointing more to the preſent purpoſe, on Pſame 64. where he ſaith, Chriſt is the Prieſt, who
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40509:11"/>being now entred into the vail alone, there of them that have been partakers of fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh, doth make interceſſion for us: In figure of which thing in that firſt people, and in that firſt Temple, the Prieſts only did enter into the Holy of Holies, and the people ſtood without. This likewiſe is the opinion and aſſertion of that famous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, learned and religious <hi>Fulk,</hi> who ſaith that Chriſt was the firſt that in his whole Humanity aſcended into Heaven. <hi>Annotat: in Apoc:</hi> 11. <hi>Sect:</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>4</label> The fourth Argument may be drawne from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of the Son of God, and the Aſſumption of our Humane nature into the ſame perſonal union of the Son of God; the Humane nature, of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt: is onely that ſmall bit, lump, portion of mans nature in general, which God according to his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal decree &amp; purpoſe before all time, <hi>Eph:</hi> 1.11. &amp; 3.11. And promiſe, and performance in time, <hi>Gen:</hi> 3.15. <hi>Eſay</hi> 9.6. <hi>Joh:</hi> 1.14. <hi>Galat:</hi> 4.4. did vouchſafe and condeſcend in free grace, and mercy to aſſume, and take unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo to become married thereunto in the unitie of the ſame perſon, unto all eternitie. Surely this is the ſumme and ſenſe of theſe promiſes, <hi>Gen:</hi> 3.15. <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall break the ſerpents head.</hi> And <hi>Hoſ:</hi> 2.19. ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will betroth thee unto mee for ever; yea. I will betroth thee unto mee in righteouſneſs, and in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in loving kindneſs, and in mercies:</hi> which gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and moſt precious promiſes, though made by God to his elect in Chriſt, and are in an inferior, ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary, and ſubordinate degree, and meaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lfilled, and diſcharged, in all, and each, and every one of them (for not one of them but in due time by Chriſts grace <hi>ſhall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40509:11"/>tread down Satan under his feet, Rom:</hi> 16.20. not one of them but <hi>is betrothed, and eſpouſed to Chriſt in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for ever:</hi>) yet howſoever, primarily, and in the firſt place, are they principally, and completely fulfilled in Chriſt himſelf, <hi>in whom all the promiſes of God are yea, and Amen.</hi> For he is that in the primeſt ſenſe (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Apoſtles expoſition, <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.16.) <hi>the ſeed of the woman,</hi> that doth bruiſe, and batter the ſerpents head, <hi>and thorough death, deſtroy him that had the power of death,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>the Devil.</hi> His fleſh, his blood, his humane nature it is, in the firſt, higheſt, and ſublimeſt ſenſe, that is betrothed, and eſpouſed unto the Lord, in righteouſneſs for ever; and in him was this promiſe, chiefly, and principally fulfilled, when <hi>God was manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the fleſh, when the word was made fleſh and dwelt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us. Joh:</hi> 1.14. This is the ſenſe and meaning of that ſoul-gladding expreſſion, and promiſe, <hi>Eſay</hi> 9 6. <hi>Unto us a child is borne, unto us a Son is given, &amp;c.</hi> In which words the holy Spirit joynes, and marries God and man together, in the unitie of the ſame perſon, to all eternity; for what is this child that is borne? but the man Chriſt Jeſus. And what is this Son that is given? but the eternall Son of God, <hi>Who ſo loved the world, that he gave his onely begotten Son, that whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life. Joh:</hi> 6.16. The ſame is the ſenſe, and meaning of that expreſſion of wiſdome it ſelf: <hi>Prov:</hi> 9 1. <hi>Wiſdome hath built her a houſe, &amp;c:</hi> Who, or what is this wiſdome? But the eternal Son of God himſelf, <hi>Chriſt the power of God, and the wiſdome of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1.24. And what is this houſe that is built? but his humane body, even
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40509:12"/>the ſame of which Chriſt by his eternal ſpirit, ſpeakes unto his Heavenly father, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. according to the tranſlation of the 70. A body haſt thou prepared me; The ſame of which he ſpeaketh to the Jewes in another place, <hi>Deſtroy this Temple, and in three daies I will build it up, Joh:</hi> 2.19. This is that holy houſe, that divine, and Heavenly Temple. So Chriſt and his Diſciples call it, <hi>Joh:</hi> 2.19., 25. <hi>In which dwelleth all the fulneſs of the Goahead bodily, Coloſ:</hi> 2.9. The ſacred rendevous, or meeting place, wherein God and man meet together, to hold an enterparle, and treaty after a long, and mortal enmity, and hoſtilitie; and to conclude (both to the glory of God, and joy of men and Angels) an everlaſting peace. That holy and heavenly Herald S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> thus trumpeteth out, and proclaimeth to the world, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, and reconciliation, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.19. <hi>God was in Chriſt reconciling the world to himſelf.</hi> In this perſonal union God ſhews himſelf to be reconciled to our Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature; takes upon him to renew it, by deriving his righteouſneſs, and holineſs through the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſt, as through a channel, or pipe of convei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, to as many of the ſin-ſick ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi> as he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dues with true faith to receive it. The Humane nature of Chriſt is that little leaven, that leaveneth the whole maſſe and lump of all true believers, by meanes of that <hi>is he made to us of God, wiſdome, and righteouſneſs, and ſanctification, and redemption,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 1. <hi>ult: To redeem us from all iniquity, and purifie unto himſelf a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uliar people zealous of good workes, Tit:</hi> 2.14. <hi>For if the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot be holy, ſo are the branches, and he that ſanctifieth, and they that are ſanctified are one,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb:</hi> 2.11. And the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40509:12"/>ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.19. <hi>That it pleaſed the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that in Chriſt all fulneſs ſhould dwell.</hi> And another, <hi>That of his fulneſs have we all received, and grace for grace. Job:</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p>Now then if the fleſh, and blood of our Dear Lord, and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, was the firſt of all other, that the eternal Son of God vouchſafed, and condeſcended to betroth, and eſpouſe to himſelf, in righteouſneſs, and true holineſs; for which cauſe <hi>that holy thing that was borne of the Virgin, was called the Son of God, Luk:</hi> 1.35. Shall we think that the ſame fleſh and blood, being thus gloriouſly deck't, and trim'd with the robes of moſt full and perfect righteouſneſs, and holineſs as the bride fitted and prepared for the bridegroome; after it had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed it's courſe here on earth, was not firſt of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, led home by the bridegroom, the eternal Son of God to his own Fathers houſe, ſo to <hi>enter into the Kings pallace, Pſ:</hi> 45.15. and to be made partakers of his glory, <hi>even his own glory, Luk:</hi> 24.26. <hi>which he had with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before the world was, Job:</hi> 17.5. eſpecially ſince Chriſt himſelf ſo plainly avoucheth, and declareth; That <hi>no man hath aſcended up into heaven, but he that came downe from heaven, even the Son of man which is in heaven, Joh.</hi> 3.13. The ſumme of this Argument may be recollected, and rendred in this Enthymeme, Chriſt's humane body was the firſt that had the grace &amp; honour of Aſſumption and perſonal union into the Divine nature; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it alone had the firſt honour, and dignity of evecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and exalt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion unto glory.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>5</label> A fifth Argument is afforded us, from thoſe places of Scripture, wherein the Apoſtle calls Chriſt the head of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40509:13"/>the Church, <hi>Eph:</hi> 1.22. <hi>And hath given him to be the head over all things to the Church, that we may grow up in him in all things which is the head, even Chriſt, Eph:</hi> 4.15. <hi>Chriſt is the head of the body, Coloſſ:</hi> 1.18. Now I ſuppoſe there is no man ſo headleſs, ſo ſenſleſs, ſo ſottiſh, but that he very well knoweth, and underſtandeth where the ſite, the place, the poſition of the head in the body naturall is. Concerning the fabrick of man's body, and it's aſpect, the Heathen Poët tells, <hi>Ovid: Metamorph: lib:</hi> 1.
<q>
                  <l>Os homini ſublime dedit, Coelum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> videre</l>
                  <l>Juſſit, &amp; erectos ad ſidera tollere vultus.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In which Diſtich the Poët intimates unto us, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the head's perſpicacitie, but alſo it's ſublimitie; not only that it of all the members, looks up to Heaven, but that it of all the members likewiſe is higheſt, and nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt unto Heaven. So the Apoſtle S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth, and aſſureth us likewiſe, that the head is the <hi>moſt honourable of all the members of the body,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 11.4. and 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.23. And being the moſt honourable of all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body, (according to our Saviours own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.) Therefore it both deſerveth, <hi>and poſſeſſeth the higheſt place, Luk.</hi> 14.8, 9. And for this cauſe as it hath the priority of all the other members in the birth, ſo hath it the preeminence, and prority in progreſſive mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without doubt it hath in an aſcendent motion wherein the head being the higheſt member, muſt of neceſſity, poſſeſſe, and occupie each place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other members of the body, and <hi>Dato, ſed non conceſſo,</hi> that <hi>Elias</hi> was coached by Angels up into
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40509:13"/>Heaven, yet can I never be perſwaded, that he was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried up thither, with his heels upward.</p>
            <p>Chriſt therefore being the head of the Church, as the Apoſtle teacheth, muſt of neceſſity (as the head in the body natural) have <hi>the preeminence in All things, Coloſ:</hi> 1.18. And therefore the priority, and prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of all his members, in reſpect of ingreſs, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into Heaven; otherwiſe he could not, he ſhould not have the preeminence in all things, nor could the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Heb:</hi> 6.20. rightly, and properly terme him our forerunner into Heaven, if any other man did outrun him thither, or run before him, for <hi>is eſt primus, ante quem nullus;</hi> He is properly the firſt of all other, before whom there is no other, ſaith <hi>Tertul: lib: de carne Chriſti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>6</label> The ſixth and laſt Argument that I ſhall raiſe for the poſitive, or affirmative part, is drawn, and taken from the Dominion, and roialtie of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, Chriſt not only as God, but alſo as man, and Mediator; <hi>Is alone the Lord of Glory,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.8. <hi>The Prince of the Kings of the earth, Apoc:</hi> 1.5. <hi>He is the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, Apoc:</hi> 10.16. and chap. 17.14. The Son of the Eternal God; <hi>whom the Father hath appointed heir of all things, Heb:</hi> 1.2. According to that witneſs, and teſtimony of the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> cited by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Math:</hi> 22.44. <hi>The Lord ſaid unto my Lord, ſit thou on my right hand, till I make thine enemies thy footſtoole, Pſal:</hi> 110.1. And all this I ſay is Chriſt, not only as he is <hi>true God.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 5.20. but alſo as he is <hi>man, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, Math:</hi> 28.18. For as he ceaſed not to be the true, and eternal God, when he was a dead man hanging on
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40509:14"/>the Croſſe, <hi>Act:</hi> 20.28. So ceaſed he not to be King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, even at the loweſt ſtep of Humiliation, when he had <hi>taken upon him the form of a ſervant, Philip:</hi> 2.7. For which cauſe the Apoſtle Saint <hi>John</hi> in his Revelation, chap. 19.16. aſcribeth, and affix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this badge, and title of Honour to Chriſt's Humane nature, ſaying, <hi>That he had on his veſture, and on his thigh a name written, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords.</hi> And Chriſt himſelf in the daies of his fleſh, and humiliation, ſtanding before <hi>Pilate,</hi> to be examined upon intergato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to <hi>Pilate's</hi> demand, <hi>Art thou a King?</hi> Denies it not, but anſwered Affirmatively, and by way of conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and grant, <hi>thou ſaiſt that I am a King; to this end was I borne, and for this cauſe came I into the world, that I ſhould bear witneſs unto the truth; every one that is of the truth, heareth my voyce, Job:</hi> 18.37. <hi>&amp;c:</hi> This was the end of Chriſt's coming into the world, to preach the truth; <hi>to gather his Saints together, Pſal:</hi> 50.5. to raiſe his Church and Kingdome, to ſummon his Subjects; and <hi>to gather together in one, the Children of God that were ſcattered abroad, Epheſ:</hi> 1.10. <hi>Joh:</hi> 11.52.</p>
            <p>Chriſt having finiſhed the great worke of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here on earth, which his Father ſent him to do, <hi>Joh:</hi> 17.4. returned then again to his Heavenly Father, from whom he came, <hi>Joh:</hi> 16.28. In the name of all his elect, to appear in the ſight of God; and to take poſſeſſion of that Kingdome, which it pleaſed the Heavenly Father to confer, and beſtow upon them, <hi>Luk:</hi> 10.32. And which <hi>he prepared for them from the foundation of the world. Math:</hi> 25.24. This very thing Chriſt himſelfe teſtifies, and intimates to his Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>Joh:</hi> 14.2,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40509:14"/>3. <hi>In my Father's houſe are many manſions, if it were not ſo I would have told you, I go to prepare a place for you and if I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again; and receive you unto my ſelf, that where I am, there ye may be alſo.</hi> In which words our Saviour comforts the hearts of his Deſciples, at his departure from them, telling them, that he was even going to Heaven, nevertheleſs, that it was expedient for them, that he went away, <hi>John</hi> 16.7. becauſe he went to heaven, to take poſſeſſion of that place, and Kingdome, not only in his own behalfe, that he might raign there himſelf alone, but alſo as their Captain, Leader, and Fore-runner, that he might take poſſeſſion of it likewiſe in their behalf, that where he is they might be alſo.</p>
            <p>The very ſelf ſame thing doth Chriſt Symbolize, and ſhaddow unto us under the Type, and Figure of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Noble man, that went into a far country, <hi>to recive for himſelf a Kingdome, and to return: Luk:</hi> 19.12. There is no doubt to be made, but by this certaine Noble man is ment the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by the far country Heaven, by the Kingdome the glorious King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven; by the receiving of this Kingdome, Chriſt's bodily Inveſtiture into it, when having by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf purged our ſins, he roſe triumphantly over death, aſcended up into Heaven, and as Lord, and Heir of all things, <hi>Sate down on the right hand of the Majeſtie on High, Heb:</hi> 1.3. <hi>far above all Principalitie, and Power, Might, and, Dominion, and every name that is named, not only in this world, but alſo in that which is to come, Eph:</hi> 1.21. <hi>who is gone into Heaven</hi> (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> of Chriſt) <hi>And is on the right hand of God, Angels, and Authorities,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40509:15"/>and Powers, being made ſubject unto him,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 3.22. This is the ſixth and laſt Argument for the poſitive part, Chriſt as man, and Mediator, being heir of all things, as a ſon and heir of his own houſe, took Frſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Kingdome of Heaven; therefore as man he made the firſt entrance into it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob:</hi> If any here except, and ſay, Though it be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that ſome men in their body, and in their fleſh, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into Heaven before Chriſt, yet this is no diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or derogation from Chriſt, ſo it likewiſe gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that Chriſt entred firſt in his Humane body as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol:</hi> Anſwer, that the grant of this courteſie is ſcarce worth the acceptation; there is no doubt to be made, but that Chriſt as Redeemer, took firſt poſſeſſion of the Kingdome of Heaven; <hi>for there is but one Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.5. <hi>And him hath the Father appointed Lord, and heir of all things. Heb:</hi> 1.3. But thus I Argue, and reaſon from the former grant; Chriſt of all men is the only Saviour, and Redeemer, therefore he alone, and firſt of all men, in his Humane body, entred into the Kingdome of Heaven. As the Apoſtle S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> expreſly ſaith, that Chriſt's precious blood was <hi>our Redemption,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.19, 20. So <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 1.14. The Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> intimates plainly enough, that the ſame precious blood, was <hi>the price, and redemption of the purchaſed poſſeſſion</hi> of the Kingdome of Heaven in our behalf: And if Chriſt alone by his body, and blood, purchaſed the Kingdom of Heaven in our behalf, all the reaſon in the world, that he himſelf ſhould firſt of all bodily enter
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40509:15"/>into it, and take poſſeſſion of it in our behalf. And thus much may ſuffice for the confirmation of the poſitive, and affirmative part.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Counter-part of the Queſtion diſcust.</head>
               <p>NOw for the confutation, and everſion of the nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and counterpart; know and underſtand, that the Scriptures afford no Apodeictical, or demonſtrative Arguments at all, and but few, yea very few Topical, or probable Arguments to ſtrengthen, ſupport, and uphold it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. The firſt, and moſt ancient that I can diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, is the example of <hi>Henoch,</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam;</hi> of whom <hi>Moſes</hi> witneſſeth ſaying, <hi>Gen:</hi> 5.24. <hi>And Henoch walked with God, and he was not, for God took him,</hi> ſaith the Text; therefore may ſome conclude, that Chriſt was not the firſt that bodily aſcended, and entred there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol:</hi> Anſw: By granting the Antecedent, and deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Conſequent, <hi>Henoch was not</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>and God took him;</hi> yet hence it follows not, that he was bodily rapt, and tranſported into Heaven without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution (as <hi>Habakkuk</hi> was tranſported <hi>thorough the vehemencie of the ſpirit of the Lord, from Judea to Babilon</hi> as the Story ſaith; <hi>And Phillip from Gaza, or thereabouts, to Azotus. Act:</hi> 8.26, 40.) For what is there in this. Text ſpoken of <hi>Henoch</hi> which cauſe us ſo to thinke, which is not in other places of Scripture, ſpoken of other the Saints, and deer children of God?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40509:16"/>And yet from them we never did, nor could conclude, that they were bodily tranſported into Heaven. Is it ſaid of <hi>Henoch</hi> he was not; and is not the ſame phraſe, and forme of ſpeech uſed by <hi>Jeremy,</hi> lamenting the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and deſolation of the Jewes: Chapter 10.20. <hi>My children are gone forth of mee, and they are not. By Rachel weeping for her children, and refuſing to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted for her children, becauſe they were not, Jer:</hi> 31.15. And likewiſe by <hi>Jacob,</hi> concerning his two ſons, <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Simeon; Joſeph is not, and Simeon is not. Gen:</hi> 42.36. And <hi>Joſeph's</hi> brethren to <hi>Joſeph</hi> living, and ſtanding before them, concerning himſelf, ſuppoſed to be dead, <hi>Gen:</hi> 42.15. <hi>Thy ſervants are</hi> 12. <hi>brethren, the ſons of one man in the Land of Canaan, and behold the youngeſt is this day with our father, and one is not.</hi> This phraſe of Scripture therefore, <hi>he is not,</hi> or, <hi>they are not,</hi> ſignifies nothing elſe, but the diſſolution, and death of a man departed this life; and by death ſeparated, and ſequeſtred from the face of the earth; that he may <hi>behold man no more with the inhabitants of the world. Eſay</hi> 38.11. And in ſenſe it anſwereth to that phraſe uſed amongſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, concerning one dead, and departed out of this life, <hi>Abiit ad plures,</hi> he is gone to more company; or, he is gone to the greater number: and that other of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews, uſed to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>He went to his Fathers;</hi> or, <hi>He was buried with his Fathers.</hi> 1 <hi>King:</hi> 14, 31. 2 <hi>King:</hi> 14.20. Thus the Lord himſelf told <hi>Abraham, Thou ſhalt go to thy Fathers in peace.</hi> (And what that phraſe meaneth the words following do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, and declare,) <hi>And be buried in a good old Age. Gen:</hi> 15.15.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40509:16"/>
               <p>Secondly, It is ſaid of <hi>Henoch,</hi> that <hi>God tooke him;</hi> and what though? muſt we therefore of neceſſitie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that like Chriſt his Saviour, <hi>He was taken up both body and ſoul into Heaven? Act:</hi> 1, 2, 9, 10, 11. Why then may we not by the ſame rule conclude the like cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall aſſumption of thoſe bleſſed Saints, and ſervants of God, of whom the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> proclaimes. Chap: 57.1. where the ſame phraſe is uſed. <hi>The righteous pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth, and no man layeth it to heart, and the mercifull are taken away</hi> (by whom? <hi>By none but God:) none con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the righteous is taken away from the evil to come.</hi> The ſame phraſe, and form of ſpeech doth the Lord himſelfe uſe, concerning <hi>Ezechiel's</hi> wife; <hi>Behold I take from thee the deſire of thine eyes: Ezech:</hi> 24.16. And <hi>Jonah</hi> to the Lord concerning himſelf: <hi>Now O Lord take I beſeech thee, my life from mee: Jonah</hi> 4.3. All theſe Saints were taken away by God, as well as <hi>Henoch;</hi> yet are we not able thence to conclude their evection, and tranſportation, both in body and ſoul into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven. In like manner ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> of <hi>Henoch, God took him;</hi> to wit by death removing him from the company of men. And the wiſe man <hi>Wiſd:</hi> 4.11. ſaith of him, <hi>that he was ſpeedily taken away, leſt that wickedneſs ſhould alter his underſtanding, or deceipt beguile his ſoul.</hi> Even by the ſelf-ſame forme of ſpeech of all the world, and in the very ſame ſenſe, as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the righteous are taken away from the evill to come.</hi> By the example of <hi>Abraham, Gen:</hi> 15.15. of good King <hi>Ezechiah,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 20.18, 19. and likewiſe of King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>King:</hi> 22.20. Becauſe from the time, and age of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch,</hi> the Church, of God began to be corrupted, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40509:17"/>the true worſhip of God to be perverted, by means of the converſation, and commixture of the ſons of God, to wit, thoſe of the poſterity of <hi>Seth,</hi> with the daughters of men, to wit, thoſe of the poſterity of <hi>Cain,</hi> therefore this ereption, and aſſumption of <hi>Henoch</hi> by God out of this world, all this while doth not prove his aſſumption both in body and ſoule into Heaven; nay the Author of that book of Wiſdome, (whoſoever he was, whether <hi>Solomon</hi> or <hi>Philo Judaeus,</hi> I know not, God knowes) is ſo far from thinking him corporally alive, that indeed he eſteemeth him among other righteous men corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally dead; as plainly appeares by what he ſaith <hi>v.</hi> 16. by way of application unto <hi>Henoch; Thus the righteous that is dead, ſhall condemne the ungodly which are living.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But though the righteous be taken away, and by God, as <hi>Henoch</hi> was, yet it is to be ſuppoſed, that they are not taken away, after the ſame manner, as was <hi>Henoch.</hi> I eaſily grant it, for of him ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> in <hi>Heb:</hi> 11. <hi>In ſolito modo Henoch Deus à terrâ ſubduxerit.</hi> God withdrew <hi>Henoch</hi> after an unuſual manner from the earth. And of him ſaith the Author of the book of Wiſdome, Chap: 4.10. <hi>He pleaſed God, and was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of him; ſo that living amongſt ſinners he was tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> The ſame ſaith the wiſe <hi>Syracides, Ecclus</hi> 44.16. So doth <hi>Paul, By faith</hi> Henoch <hi>was tranſlated, that he ſhould not ſee death:</hi> Heb: 11.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> I grant that <hi>Henoch</hi> was tranſlated; (for ſo ſaith the Scripture) but concerning the manner how? and the place whither? <hi>Adhuc ſub Judice lis eſt;</hi> there is the queſtion; for in the Scripture we read of a tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to grace, as well as of a tranſlation to glory, 1 <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſ:</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40509:17"/>13. The Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>That God hath tranſlated us, into the Kingdome of his deer Son.</hi> And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, he hath not as yet tranſported us both body and ſoule, into the glorious Kingdome of Heaven. That <hi>Henoch's</hi> tranſlation ſhould conſiſt in the evection, and exaltation of his Humane body into Heaven, I can hardly grant, for this (as I conceive) would quite evert, and overthrow that aſſertion of the Apoſtle, that <hi>Chriſt is the firſt fruits of thoſe that ſlept.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 15. and that other of the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>That Chriſt in all things hath the preeminence, Coloſſ:</hi> 1.18. Yea and that ſaying of Chriſt himſelfe alſo, <hi>Joh:</hi> 3.13. <hi>No man hath aſcended up into heaven, but he that came down from heaven, even the Son of man which is in heaven.</hi> And if I muſt needs erre concerning one, I will rather chuſe to detract ſomething from the honour &amp; repute of <hi>Henoch,</hi> then derogate the leaſt jot, or title from the glory, honour, &amp; preeminence of Chriſt. Sure I am that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> is ſo far from avouching the body of <hi>Henoch</hi> to be in Heaven, that he condemneth it of curioſitie to enquire what is become of him, or to what end he was tranſlated. <hi>Hom: Heb:</hi> 22. <hi>&amp; Jer:</hi> 21.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob:</hi> But of <hi>Henoch</hi> the Apoſtle ſaith, that he was ſo tranſlated <hi>that he ſhould not ſee death. Heb:</hi> 11.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol:</hi> The ſame ſaith Chriſt of every true believer, <hi>Joh:</hi> 8.51. <hi>Verily, verily I ſay unto you, if a man keep my ſaying he ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll never ſee death:</hi> yet every one that believes in Chriſt, and keeps his ſaying, is not forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with corporally tranſlated to eternal life. It is plain, and manifeſt, that theſe words of Chriſt cannot be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the exemption from corporal, but of the evaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40509:18"/>of eternal death, as plainly appeares by the Jewes anſwer to our Saviour <hi>v.</hi> 52. <hi>Abraham is dead, and the Prophets are dead:</hi> yet thoſe holy men of God, believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Chriſt are truly ſaid by Chriſt not to ſee, that is, not to feele the ſting of death; becauſe in the midſt of death, by true faith, they have a ſight of eternal life. <hi>Job</hi> 8.5, 6. ſaith Chriſt to the Jewes, <hi>Your father Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham rejoyced to ſee my daies, and he ſaw it, and was glad.</hi> As in the former ſentence, <hi>not to ſee,</hi> is not to feel; ſo in the latter, <hi>to ſee,</hi> is by faith to enjoy.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg: </seg>2</label> A ſecond Argument may be taken from the example of <hi>Elias,</hi> of him the Scripture teſtifies, <hi>That he went up by a whirle-wind into heaven,</hi> 2 <hi>King:</hi> 2.11. The wiſe Syracides likewiſe celebrates him with this Encomium, <hi>That he was taken up in a whirle-wind of fire, and in a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, of fiery horſes, Ecclus</hi> 48.9. <hi>He was taken up in a whirlewind of fire,</hi> ſaith the Apocriphal book, <hi>by a whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind into heaven,</hi> ſaith the Canonical; and what though? ſhall we hence infer, that therefore he was tranſported body and ſoul into the emperial Heaven without diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution? it doth not follow, we well know, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is lifted up from the earth, &amp; that doth encircle, and encompaſſe the earth, in Scripture phraſe, is called by the name of heaven, (for from hence the name of heaven is deriv'd, for that it is hoven up above, or from the earth, ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Verſtegan.</hi>) In the Scriptures we read of the <hi>fowles of heaven, Job</hi> 35.11. By that can be meant nothing elſe but the air, as plainly doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from <hi>Gen:</hi> 6.7. and <hi>Math:</hi> 6.26. compared toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In the Scriptures likewiſe we read of the <hi>Stars of Heaven, Gen:</hi> 22.17. By Heaven there can nothing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40509:18"/>els be ment, but the Celeſtial orbs; for as the Emperial Heaven, that hath no need of Sun, Moon, or Stars, or any of thoſe petty, or inferiour lights, as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth in his Revelation Chap: 21.23. <hi>The City had no need of the Sun, neither of the Moon to ſhine in it: for the glory of God did lighten it: and the Lamb was the light thereof.</hi> In the Scripture likewiſe we read of a <hi>third Heaven</hi> whither Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was rapt, which by <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 12.4. <hi>Joh: Apoc:</hi> 2.7. And Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Luk:</hi> 23.43. <hi>is called Paradiſe.</hi> And again by Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Abraham's boſome, Luk.</hi> 16. And <hi>his fathers houſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are many manſions. Joh:</hi> 14.2. So that <hi>Elias,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this Trimembred diſtinction may be carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven, and yet be elevated no higher, and paſſe no further then the air; yet if this Anſwer ſeems too poor, hungry, and ſtarvling; be it granted that <hi>Elias</hi> was tranſported into the higheſt, and Emperial Heaven, yet as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of himſelf, and of his own rapture, into the ſame place; ſo may I ſay of <hi>Elias, whether it was in the body I cannot tell; or whether it was out of the body I cannot tell; God knowes.</hi> Still I thinke the ſafeſt way will be; (that nothing may be derogated from the prerogative of Chriſt.) To conclude that his ſpirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned unto God that gave it; yeelding over his body into the hands, and ſecret wiſdome, and councel of God to be diſpoſed of, and reſolved as he thought good. And why may we not ſay, that the body of <hi>Elias</hi> upon his ſpirits returne into the hands of the father of Spirits: was reſolved into its mother earth by the power of God, even by the ſame omnipotent power, by which Humane bodies were prepared, and accommodated, for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40509:19"/>the holy and heavenly Angels, that appeared to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Lot,</hi> and others; (certainly they had true bodies, as appeares by their eating, drinking; the waſhing of their feet, and the performance of other Humane Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and this is the opinion of <hi>Michael Pſellus,</hi> the beſt Doemoniſt that ever wrote, ſaith <hi>Joh: Luaovicus vives,</hi> both concerning Angels, and Devils; as he derives it from the great S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Baſil</hi> in his book of the operation of Devils;) which immediately after the execution, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch, and finiſhing of their embaſſage, and diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were by the ſame Almighty power of God, either annihilated, or reſolved into their firſt principles.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg: </seg>3</label> The third probabilitie is raiſed from the example of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> who at Chriſt's Transfiguration on the holy mount, are ſaid to have <hi>appeared unto Jeſus, and to have ſpoken unto him of his diſceaſe, which he ſhould accompliſh at Jeruſalem; Math:</hi> 17.3. <hi>Marc:</hi> 9.4. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.30, 31. The objection as I conceive may be thus for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and faſhioned; <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> appeared in glory to Jeſus on the holy mount in their Humane bodies from Heaven: therefore Chriſt was not the firſt that entred into heaven with humane body, becauſe if the two former brought their bodies along with them from heaven, it is likely they carried the ſame bodies along with them to heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">sol. </seg>
                  </label> Anſw: That this Argument hath contain'd in it three Articles, or petty queſtions; Firſt whether <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> appeared unto our Saviour with true, real, and ſubſtantial humane bodies? 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, whether they were the very ſelf ſame Humane bodies, and earthly tabernacles wherewith they were inveſted, and cloathed, during
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40509:19"/>their peregrination, and pilgrimage here on earth? Thirdly, whether brought theſe their bodies from Heaven?</p>
               <p>Though I may eaſily grant, that they appeared to our Saviour in true, real, and ſubſtantial, Humane bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as may eaſily be concluded, and confirmed from thoſe bodily, and corporal actions, that they perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on the mount, ſpeaking and diſcourſing with our Saviour face to face, concerning his death, and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that he was to accompliſh at Jeruſalem: And though I eaſily grant in a ſecond place, that thoſe true, and real bodies, were the ſame bodies wherewith their ſoules were cloathed whiles they were on earth; (for had their bodies bin others, they could not properly have been ſaid to be <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias:)</hi> yet cannot I ſo eaſily grant in the third place, that they brought their bodies along with them from Heaven. Full well I know, that it was an opinion embraced by many, yea very many of the Ancient Fathers, that the bodies of <hi>Henoch,</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> are reſerved and kept alive in a third manſion houſe, diſtinct and ſeparate both from Heaven, and earth, which they call Paradiſe; and that they ſhall returne, and bodily appear on the earth, before the day of Judgment; yea, and <hi>John</hi> the Divine, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremie</hi> too, whoſe death is not read of; ſaith <hi>Hyppolitus.</hi> If this opinion be true, then doubtleſſe <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> brought not their bodies from Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with them to the holy mount.</p>
               <p>But leaving that opinion as we found it, concerning <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Scripture plainly concludeth concerning him that his body went not to Heaven together with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40509:20"/>his ſoul. <hi>Deut:</hi> 34.5, 6. there we read: <hi>So Moſes the ſervant of the Lord died in the land of Moab, according to the word of the Lord, and he</hi> (that is either God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or an Angel of God.) <hi>buried him in a valley in the land of Moab; over againſt Beth Peor, but no man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of his Sepulcre unto this day.</hi> And this, as I conceive, accaſioned that grave, and ſolemne diſpute, and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie (according to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Judes</hi> Eccleſiaſtical tradition, and relation, <hi>v.</hi> 9. of his Epiſtle betwixt <hi>Michael the Archangel &amp; the devil, about the body of Moſes:</hi> The devil urging, as I conceive, the neceſſity of the revelation of the place of ſepulture thereof, that by that meanes he might yeeld the Jewes a copious, and abundant occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of committing Idolatry, who he well knew were apt enough by nature, to honour God's faithfull ſervant too much, and to neglect his Lord. Contrariwiſe the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Angel preſſing home, the expediencie, and neceſſitie of the concealment of it's place of burial, for the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and diſappointing of the occaſion, and introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Superſtition and Idolatry.</p>
               <p>Wherefore if the body of <hi>Moſes</hi> went not together with his ſoul to heaven, but as the Scripture teacheth, remained on earth, then ſurely could he not bring it along with him from heaven, when he appeared on the holy mount; and why may not the ſame be ſaid of <hi>Elias,</hi> that his body by the hand of God's omnipotencie, had as ſudden a reſtitution at his ſoul's deſcent from Heaven (the very caſe of the ſoules of God's elect at the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection) as it had diſſolution at it's evection, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation thither? Sure I am, whatſoever other men thinke, the conceipt and opinion of the ſons, of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40509:20"/>was, that his body was not carried up into heaven, but rather that the <hi>ſpirit of the Lord had taken him up, and caſt him upon ſome mountain, or into ſome valley,</hi> which made them ſo earneſtly to ſue unto <hi>Eliſha: That fifty ſtrong and able men might goe, and make ſearch, and inquiſition after him.</hi> 2 <hi>King:</hi> 2.16. And theſe ſons of the Prophets, as I conceive, were no plain, or ſimple men, but even Prophets themſelves (as man, and ſon of man, are all one in Hebrew phraſe) belonging and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the Schole, or Colledge of <hi>Elias,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha,</hi> whom a great Antiquary, and Chronologer, from prophane writers calleth by the name of <hi>Elulaeus Armagh: Chron:</hi> One objection remaineth that may be made, that ſeems ſomewhat weighty, and ponderous; it is this,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg: </seg>4</label> Chriſt had his meſſengers, and fore-runners, his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants the Prophets, going before his face to prepare his way before himſelf bodily, and perſonally oppeared in fleſh, and blood here on earth, to gather his Church, and enter upon his Kingdome of grace; what hurt then, if we ſuppoſe ſome Saints, and holy men of God, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally went before him as his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> fore-runners, and meſſengers, before he himſelf perſonally, and in his Humane body entred, and actually took poſſeſſion of his Kingdome of glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Sol."/> 
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> Be it granted, that Chriſt had his meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and fore-runners, before he came perſonally him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to plant his Church, to gather his Saints together, and to enter upon his Kingdome of grace, yet hence it follows not, that he had any that did fore-run him bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, before himſelf bodily, and perſonally entred into
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40509:21"/>his Kingdome of glory. A neceſſity there was of the Antecedent, but no neceſſity at all of the Conſequent. For the better, and clearer Demonſtration of my ſenſe, and meaning in this Anſwer, we muſt obſerve, and mark, that the whole my ſtery of man's redemption, is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and eſtabliſhed on a threefold foundation: Firſt on God's eternal purpoſe before all time. Secondy, on his free promiſe at the beginning of time. Thirdly, on his mercifull performance in the fulneſs of time.</p>
               <p>The firſt is God's eternal purpoſe before all time: of this we muſt conceive thus: that God, to whoſe eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall knowledge, all things are preſent, and nothing paſt, or to come, foreſeeing man's fall before all time purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſend his Son Jeſus Chriſt into the world to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem him, <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 1.9. <hi>Act:</hi> 2.23.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is, God's free promiſe at the beginning of time; when immediately upon the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> God promiſed Chriſt unto him, ſaying unto the ſerpent, <hi>I will put emnity between thee, and the woman; and between thy ſeed, and her ſeed: He</hi> (that is to ſay, Chriſt the ſeed of the woman) <hi>ſhall break thy head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe is heel.</hi> This promiſe of Chriſt the woman's ſeed, was the Goſpel, and the only comfort of <hi>Adam, Abel, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch, Methuſelah, Noah,</hi> and the reſt of the godly Fathers till the time of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At the time of <hi>Abraham,</hi> this promiſe was turned into a covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his ſeed, and oft times repeated: That <hi>in his ſeed all Nations ſhould be bleſſed. Gen:</hi> 12.3. and 18.18. and 22.18. which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and covenant was the very voice it ſelfe of the Goſpel; it being a true Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40509:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Apoſtle beareth witneſs, ſaying, <hi>Gal:</hi> 3. <hi>The Scripture foreſeeing, that God would Juſtifie the Gentiles through Faith, preached before the Goſpel unto Abraham, ſaying, In thee, or in thy ſeed ſhall all nations be bleſſed.</hi> That this promiſed ſeed was meant of Chriſt, and of him alone, the Apoſtle puts us out of all doubt, <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.16. <hi>Now to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham and his ſeed were the promiſes made, he ſaith not, and to ſeeds, as of many, but as of one, and to thy ſeed which is Chriſt.</hi> Now this Covenant thus made, and confirmed with Abraham, was renewed with Iſaak, <hi>Gen:</hi> 26.4. and made knowne unto Jacob by Jeſus Chriſt himſelf; for that man which wraſtled with Jacob, was none other, but the man Chriſt Jeſus; for himſelf ſaid, <hi>That Jacob ſhould be called Iſrael, a wreſtler, and prevailer with God: and Jacob called the name of the place Peniel, becauſe he had ſeen God face to face. Gen:</hi> 32.28, 30.</p>
               <p>Anon upon the death of theſe holy Patriarchs, God raiſed up his faithfull ſervant <hi>Moſes,</hi> who by God's command committed that to writing, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived by tradition, and word of mouth, from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Seth, Henoch,</hi> and the other Patriarches ſucceſſively to his owne time; to wit, the creation of the world; the fall of man; the promiſe of a Redeemer; the Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie of Chriſt from Adam: the propagation, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, and protection of the Church: the fearfull deſtruction, and confuſion of God's enemies: the which <hi>Moſes</hi> receiving from God a forme of eccleſiaſticall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, upon the top of mount Sinai, conſiſting in divers and ſundry ſacrifices of beaſts, and other religious
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40509:22"/>rites, and ceremonies ſhaddowed out unto the people; the ſole expiatorie, and propitiatory ſacrifice of that true Paſcal Lamb, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt which was to come; the ſame <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo being himſelf a Type, and Figure of Chriſt, yeelded forth, and uttered a moſt excellent and perſpicuous Phopheſie of Chriſt, <hi>Deut:</hi> 18.15. <hi>The Lord thy God will raiſe up unto thee a Prophet from the midſt of thee; of thy brethren like unto mee; unto him yee ſhall hearken, and it ſhall come to paſſe, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hoſoever will not hearken unto my words, which he ſhall ſpeak in my name, I will require it of him. v.</hi> 19. The which glorious propheſie of <hi>Moſes</hi> the Apoſtle S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> in that excellent Sermon of his, which he had to the people, at the beautifull gate of the Temple, concerning the lame man reſtored to his feet, applieth home to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to him only, <hi>Act:</hi> 3.12, 13.</p>
               <p>After <hi>Moſes</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Joſhua,</hi> the Captain, and Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Lord's people into the Land of Canaan; who likewiſe was a Type of Chriſt, the true <hi>Michael,</hi> Prince, <hi>and Captain of the Hoſts of the Lord. Joſhua</hi> 5.14.</p>
               <p>After <hi>Joſhua</hi> followed the <hi>Judges,</hi> whoſe reſcue, and deliverance of the Lord's people, from the tyranny of their temporal enemies, was the undoubted type, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of the eternal redemption of the Church, by Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>the Judge both of quick and dead,</hi> from the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie of their ſpiritual, and everlaſting enemies, ſin, ſatan, and condemnation: <hi>Yea, and all the Prophets from Samuel, and thoſe that followed after, as many as have ſpoken, have likewiſe foretold of theſe daies. Act:</hi> 3.24.</p>
               <p>For <hi>David,</hi> a man choſen of God after his own heart,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40509:22"/>being both a wiſe King, and a great Prophet; foreſaw the coming of Chriſt in the fleſh; foretold that he ſhould be borne of his own loynes, 132.11. <hi>The Lord hath ſworn in truth unto David; he will not turn from it; of the fruit of thy body will I ſet upon thy Throne:</hi> which words, though litterally meant of Solomon, yet typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, and myſtically, are they fulfilled in Chriſt, as may be gathered, and concluded eaſily, by applying, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring them with what he ſaith all along, thorough out the 72. Pſalm: moreover he foreſaw, and foretold both the natures of Chriſt: Firſt his humane nature, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 45.2. <hi>Thou art fairer then the children of men.</hi> Secondly his Divine, <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>Thy Throne O God is for ever, and ever; the Scepter of thy Kingdome is a right Scepter, thou loveſt righteouſneſs, and hateſt wickedneſs, therefore God, (even thy God) hath anointed thee with the oile of gladneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove thy fellows.</hi> Likewiſe he foreſaw, and foretold both the ſtates and conditions of Chriſt; both his ſtate of diſgrace, and his ſtate of glory; his ſtate of humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and his ſtate of exaltation: his ſtate of humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he intimates in thoſe words of his, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 22.6. <hi>I am a worm and no man: a reproach of men, and deſpiſed of the people.</hi> His falſe accuſation, crucifixion, bitter death, and blooddy paſſion, with the concomitant cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances thereof. He intimates in thoſe words of his, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 22.16, 17, 18. <hi>For dogs have compaſſed mee; the aſſemblies of the wicked have encloſed mee: they pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced my hands, and my feet: I may tell all my bones: they look, and ſtare upon mee: they part my garments, and caſt lots upon my veſture: Math:</hi> 27.34. That bitter
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40509:23"/>potion, that they offered him, either in pitty, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to ſtupifie him, that he might become ſenſleſs, or at leaſtwiſe leſſe ſenſible of his tortures, as ſay ſome, or elſe in ſcorne, and deriſion, as ſay others; <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> intimates in thoſe words of his, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 69.21. <hi>They gave mee alſo gall for my meat, and in my thirſt they gave mee vineger to drinke.</hi> His death, buriall, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection he intimates in thoſe words, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.8, 9, 10. <hi>I have ſet the Lord alwayes before mee, becauſe he is at my right hand, I ſhall not be moved, therefore my heart is glad, and my glory rejoyceth, my fleſh alſo ſhall reſt in hope, for thou wilt not leave my ſoule in hell, neither wilt thou ſuffer thine holy one to ſee corruption.</hi> All which words of the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi> applies to Chriſt, and to him alone, <hi>Act:</hi> 2.25, 26, 27. verſes. His aſcention he intimates in theſe words, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 68.18. <hi>Thou haſt aſcended on high, thou haſt led captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie captive.</hi> His glorious evection, and exaltation to the right hand of his holy, and heavenly Father. He point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at in theſe words, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 110.1. <hi>The Lord ſaid unto my Lord, ſit thou on my right hand, until I make thine enemies thy footſtoole.</hi> which words of <hi>David,</hi> our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our applies to himſelf, <hi>Math:</hi> 22.44. and what ſhould I more ſay? but that from the firſt iſſuing forth of the promiſe, from God in the garden of <hi>Eden;</hi> that a Meſſias ſhould come: God never ceaſed in all ages, and genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Church, either by viſions, or expreſs Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and Types to the Fathers before the Law: and Types and Figures under the Law; and plain, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt predictions by <hi>Moſes, David,</hi> and other ſucceeding
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40509:23"/>Prophets, to point out unto the world the promiſed Meſſias, and to give his people aſſurance of his coming: who propheſied the time, place, and manner of his birth: the affliction of his life, the kind of his death, the glory of his reſurrection, the deliverance of his people, the end for which he came, with all other circumſtances belonging to his manifeſtation. The laſt of all, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets (and that by Chriſt's own witneſſe, <hi>Math:</hi> 11.13.) was <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, who immediately before his coming, <hi>going before the face of the Lord, in the ſpirit, and power of Elias, to prepare his way, preacht unto the people the doctrine of repentance, and remiſsion of ſins; ſaying, repent for the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand.</hi> After the voice of this Crier, immediately followed the eternall word of the Father, in his own perſon, clothed with fleſh and blood, to preach redemption to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And here was the full performance of God's long promiſe: now then to ſit down and reſt, and breath a little after a long ramble, and chaſe, peradventure ſome may ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">queſt: </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Quorſum iſthaec tam longo repetita circuitu?</hi> What meanes this long narration of God's moſt merciſul di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation to his Church, in putting it in minde, ſome way or other, in all ages, and generations of the promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Meſſias?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">sol: </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> That the neceſſity might the better appeare, why the Father ſent the ſervants in the firſt place; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his ſon perſonally appeared in the laſt: to gather his Saints together, and to raiſe his Kingdome of grace: theſe he did for theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:40509:24"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt for the better calling to mind, and keeping his promiſe in perpetual remembrance. For ſince from the firſt going forth of the promiſe, and the performance thereof, in the fulneſſe of time, by the incarnation, and nativitie of the Son of God, ſo great a Chaſme, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terval of time did intercede, as the ſpace, and length of almoſt 4000. yeares, according to the computation, and account of <hi>Beroaldus;</hi> had not God ſome way, or other, as ſaith <hi>Paul Heb:</hi> 1.1. either by viſions, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, tradition, Types, and Figures, Propheſies, and Predictions of his ſervants the Prophets, ſucceſſively ſent in all ages, continually call'd his promiſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance; and preſerved and kept it freſh in the minds of his people: in all reaſon his promiſe in ſo long a tract, and duration of time, would have been forgotten, and the whole world have fell into a general, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal atheiſme, and apoſtacie: faith unfeigned in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and in him alone, being the undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and infallible ground worke, and foundation of true, and ſound religion, towards God: ſo ſaith Chriſt to his heavenly Father. <hi>And this is life eternal, to know thee the only true God, and whom thou hast ſent Jeſus Chriſt. Joh:</hi> 17.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, he did it for the ſtrengthning the faith of all true believers; which elſe through the weakneſſe, and infirmitie of the fleſh, had been apt every moment to faile, had not God in all ages, from the creation down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, by ſome means, and meſſenger or other, ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, and refreſht his promiſe to his Church: I ſay from the iſſuing forth of the firſt promiſe, concerning
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40509:24"/>the Meſſias, from God in Paradiſe, to the performance thereof, there being ſo long a tract, and continuation of time, as the ſpace of almoſt 4000 years: had not God continually ſeconded, and backt his firſt promiſe, with freſh, and new promiſes to his Church in all ages; the faith of God's children had bin apt, yea very apt to faile: and not without cauſe might they have cried out, and complained with <hi>David, Pſal:</hi> 69.3. <hi>Mine eies faile while I wait for my God</hi> and 119.82. <hi>Mine eies faile for thy word: ſaying, when wilt thou comfort mee?</hi> and 119.123. <hi>Mine eies faile for thy ſalvation, and for the word of thy righteouſneſſe.</hi> And as he doth <hi>Pſal:</hi> 77.7, 8. <hi>Will the Lord caſt off for ever? and will he be favourable no more? Is his mercy clean gone for ever? doth his promiſe faile for evermore?</hi> And for this cauſe God made the Saints of all ages, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Heb:</hi> 6.12. tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough faith, and patience to inherit the promiſe, both of the coming, and incarnation of the Son of God, that ſo both they, and we might be made one. (<hi>Chriſt,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Paul, having broken down the middle wall of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between us, Epheſ:</hi> 2.14.) And ſo as Saint <hi>Peter, All of us be ſaved, through the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Act:</hi> 15.11. We by faith in Chriſt that is come: they by the ſame faith in Chriſt that was to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Thirdly, this he did to whet and ſharpen the deſires, and heighten the hope, and expectation of his ſervants. The wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> yeelds us a moſt excellent ſaying to this purpoſe, <hi>Prov:</hi> 13.12. <hi>Hope deferred maketh the heart ſick, but when the deſire cometh, it is a tree of life.</hi> In which golden Text, hope is ſet for the thing ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40509:25"/>for, as it is likewiſe <hi>Heb:</hi> 6.18. And this hope de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, and delai'd, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> maketh the heart ſick; that is, to ſigh, and groan earneſtly, with deſire and love, and longing after the thing hoped for. Thus the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> by a moſt elegant proſopopoeia <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.21, 22. maketh the whole creature, the whole creation, <hi>to groan, and travel in pain together, to be delivered from the bondage of corruption, into the glorious libertie of the Sons of God.</hi> Thus the Church <hi>grew ſick</hi> with deſire, and longing ſhe had after Chriſt, <hi>Cantic:</hi> 2.5. and 5.8. Thus <hi>Jacob waited for the Lords ſalvation, Gen:</hi> 49.18. And <hi>David longed for it, Pſal:</hi> 119.174. And <hi>his ſoule panted, and thirſted after God,</hi> with as much vehemencie, and ardencie of deſire, <hi>as the Hart panted after the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter brooks, Pſal:</hi> 42.1, 2. Thus the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Church to ſigh and groan after the company, and fellowſhip of Chriſt, Chap: 26.8, 9. <hi>In the way of thy Judgments, O Lord, have we waited for thee: the deſire of our ſoul is to thy name, and to the remembrance of thee: with my ſoul have I deſired thee in the night, yea with my ſpirit within mee will I ſeek thee early, &amp;c:</hi> Thus <hi>Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> earneſtly looked, and longed for him; and all the Saints likewiſe, <hi>that looked for redemption in Jeruſalem. Luk:</hi> 2.38. And after the ſame manner the Apoſtles, both Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp; Saint <hi>John,</hi> make the whole Church to long after the comeing of Chriſt, and the reſtitution of all things. 2 <hi>Con:</hi> 5.2. <hi>Apoc:</hi> 22.17, 18, 20. This I ſay is the third Reaſon, why the great Lord both of Heaven, and earth, ſent ſo many of his ſervants, in the firſt place before he ſent his only Son: that ſo the world
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40509:25"/>being continually informed by the ſervants, and meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers that went before, concerning the comeing of their Lord &amp; Maſter that was to follow after: the hearts of all true believers, might be enflamed with the deſire of him, and long to ſee that day, wherein Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>the deſire of all Nations,</hi> as <hi>Haggai</hi> calls him, Chap: 2.7. ſhould come; (as the ſick patient thinks every hour two, till the Phyſitian comes, who he believes will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover him,) and at his coming receive him, the more joyfully; and glorifie the Lord the more thankfully, for that long lookt for was at laſt come: and their eies with <hi>Simeon,</hi> had ſeen the Lord's ſalvation, even the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Lord of life: who is indeed, as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Apoc:</hi> 22.2. <hi>A tree of life</hi> to every faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoul: according to the former Aphoriſme of the wiſe <hi>Solomon, Hope deferred maketh the heart ſick; but when the deſire cometh it is a tree of life Prov:</hi> 13.12.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, the ſervants went ſo long before; before the Lord, and Maſter himſelf came, that ſo the diſeaſe might have time to come to it's full height: for the ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation of <hi>Adam's</hi> ſin; that it might appear exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinfull; and the manifeſtation of the corruption of our Humane nature flowing from thence; which by moſt certain, and evident arguments, of ſo many ages, and generations, was ſo far from being bettered, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that <hi>aetas parentum pejor avis:</hi> it ſtill grew worſe and worſe: The venime of <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin was ſo ſtrong, and mortal: the gulf, and whirl-pool of his tranſgreſſion, ſo unſearchable; as ſaith <hi>Muſculus:</hi> and thereupon to give us occaſion, the more dangerous, and deſperate the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40509:26"/>diſeaſe was, the more to magnifie, and admire, the moſt profound skill of our Heavenly Phyſitian.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> Fifty, this was done for the declaration; and manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of the moſt wonderfull goodneſſe, patience, and long ſufferance of the Lord; who notwithſtanding the whole earth was filled with violence; and all fleſh had corrupted its way, for the ſpace of almoſt 4000. yeares, yet for bore all this while to deſtroy the world, for it's iniquity: and as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>winked at the times of this ignorance.</hi> And in this the Lord performed the part of a patient, and long ſuffering creditor, who ſuffers his debtors to run on long, and far in his debt, before he calls for payment, and ſatisfaction; and even then gives them mony of his own to pay the debt: ſo God ſuffered the world to run on long in skore with him; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt 4000 years, and then ſent Chriſt to pay the debt, and make ſatisfaction, <hi>whom God hath ſet forth to be a propitiation, thorough faith in his blood, to declare his righteouſneſſe for the remiſston of ſins, that are paſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the forbearance of God. Rom:</hi> 3.25.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>6</label> Sixthly, and laſtly, The Father promiſed, and ſent his ſervants ſo long before, before he ſent at laſt his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten Son; for the greater amplification, illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and magnification of the honour, and dignitie of his Son. For the greater, and more noble the perſon, the more the ſervants be to attend, and guard him; and likewiſe to run before him. This appears plainly: Firſt from that Oracle of <hi>Solom: Prov:</hi> 14.28. <hi>In the multitude of people is the Kings honour.</hi> This doubtleſſe made <hi>David</hi> in pride, and vain glory to number the people. Secondly, from <hi>Samuel</hi> inſtruction to the children
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40509:26"/>of Iſrael concerning the order, cuſtome, and manner of Kings. 1 <hi>Sam:</hi> 8.11 <hi>He will take your ſons, and appoint them for himſelf; for his chariots, and to be his horſmen: and ſome ſhall run before his chariots.</hi> And thirdly, from <hi>Abſolom</hi>'s practice; 2 <hi>Sam:</hi> 15.1. who to declare unto the world his pomp, power, and Majeſty, <hi>prepared him chariots. and horſes, and</hi> 50 <hi>men to run before him.</hi> Now if Chriſt had had no meſſengers before his face, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his way, before he came bodily, and perſonally him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into his Kingdome of grace; the royaltie, ſtate, and Majeſtie of this great Lord, and King, both of Heaven, and earth, might have well ſeemed leſſe, then that of the Centurion, who had ſouldiers under him; <hi>and who could ſay to this mangoe, and he goeth; and to another come, and he cometh; and to his ſervant do this, and he doth it: Math:</hi> 8 9. This Royall State, and Majeſtie, of Chriſt himſelfe, typifies to the life; under the Parable of <hi>a certain houſholder, that planted a vineyard, and let it it out to husbandmen, and ſent his ſervants in the firſt place, but laſt of all his only ſon, and heir, that they might receive the fruits thereof: Math:</hi> 21.33, 34. Now there is no doubt to be made, but by this houſholder is meant God the Father, whom Chriſt, <hi>Joh:</hi> 15.1. calls <hi>an huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman;</hi> by this vineyard the people of the Jewes (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the whole Church of Chriſt;) whom imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after their deliverance out of the land of Egypt, God nouriſhed 40. yeares in the wilderneſſe; and then planted as a <hi>Vineyard in a very fruitfull hill: Eſay</hi> 5.1. even the Land of Canaan, flowing with milk and hony. Of this <hi>David</hi> ſings, and tryumphs, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 81.8, 9. <hi>Thou haſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40509:27"/>brought a vine out of Egypt, thou haſt caſt out the Heathen, and planted it: thou prepared'st room for it, and didſt cauſe it to take deep root, &amp; it filled the land.</hi> By thoſe husband men are meant the Scribes, Phariſes, and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Rulers, and Governours among the Jews, who by their impietie and ill husbandry, prov'd perfidious traitors, and rebels, againſt this great houſholder in abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his ſervants the Prophets, who came firſt; and then in murthering, &amp; ſlaying his own Son, &amp; Heir, who came laſt, to demand fruits of his vineyard: and theſe are the Reaſons why Chriſt had ſo many meſſengers, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to goe before him, before he came perſonally himſelfe to erect, and raiſe up his Kingdome of grace. Theſe are the reaſons why (as ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) God at ſundry times, and in divers manners, ſpake in times paſt, unto the Fathers by the Prophets, but in theſe laſt daies, hath ſpoken to us by his Son, whom he hath appointed heir of all things. Heb:</hi> 1.1, 2.</p>
               <p>But though Chriſt had many ſervants ſtill going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, before his bodily introduction into his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of grace; yet ſtill I ſay, hence it follows not, that any of his Saints, &amp; members went before him, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented him, before his own bodily induction, &amp; inveſture into his Kingdome of glory. A neceſſity there was of the former (for the reaſons before alleaged) but there was no neceſſity at all, of the later what neceſſity could there be, that Chriſt ſhould have his forerunners in the fleſh, to goe before him; before himſelf bodily aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Kingdome of Heaven? what? to carry news to God the Father, his holy Angels, and Saints of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40509:27"/>Chriſts's tryumphant, victory over death, his reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and to inform them; that Chriſt himſelf would ſhortly bodily appear in his own perſon in Heaven? As <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> the ſon of <hi>Zadoch,</hi> ran ſpeedily to carry <hi>David</hi> good newes concerning his victory over his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious ſon <hi>Abſolom?</hi> 2 <hi>Sam:</hi> 18. there was no neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, I ſay, of all this; God, his holy Angels, and the Saints themſelves doubtleſſe by revelation from God, knew ſufficiently, that Chriſt, after he had finiſhed his paſſion, ſhould himſelf bodily <hi>enter into his glory, Lu:</hi> 24.26. <hi>For it became him for whom are all things, &amp; by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are all things, in bringing many ſons unto glory, to make the captain of their ſalvation.</hi> (and therefore their ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader) <hi>perfect thorough ſufferings Heb:</hi> 2.10. Nay there was a double neceſſity, that no fleſh, and blood ſhould enter into the Kingdome of Heaven, before Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Firſt in reſpect of Chriſt himſelf. Secondly in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his members.</p>
               <p>Firſt in reſpect of Chriſt himſelf, for if any Saint had bodily entred into heaven before Chriſt himſelf, then that Saint had bin <hi>the firſt fruits of them that ſlept,</hi> and not Chriſt. Secondly, in reſpect of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt; there was a neceſſity that ſome ſhould not enter bodily into Heaven without others, that ſo (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>Some without others might not be made perfect, Heb:</hi> 11.40. But briefly to recapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate what hath been ſpoken, a neceſſity there was that Chriſt of all men ſhould firſt enter bodily into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, for thoſe 6. cauſes, or reaſons before alleaged. 1. Thereby to declare the Analogie, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40509:28"/>between the firſt and the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Thereby to confirme that Chriſt is the firſt fruits. Thirdly, for that Chriſt is our High Prieſt, and therefore ought firſt, and before all other, to enter into the holy place. Fourthly, for that his Humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was the firſt fleſh that God aſſumed; and therefore in all reaſon ought it firſt to be glorified. Fifthly, for that Chriſt is the head of the Church; therefore to him belongeth the Preeminence of the firſt entrance. Sixth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for that Chriſt is the Lord, and heir of all things; therefore to him appertaineth the firſt entrance, and poſſeſſion of the Kingdome of Heaven. To theſe may be added <hi>vice coronidis</hi> in the ſeaventh and laſt place, the confirmation, and eſtabliſhment of divers, and ſundry expreſſe teſtimonies of the Scriptures, all avouching, and confirming the ſame thing, that Chriſt firſt of all bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily aſcended, and entred into Heaven. <hi>Joh:</hi> 3.13. ſaith Chriſt, <hi>No man hath aſcended up into heaven, but he that came down from Heaven, even the Son of man which is in Heaven.</hi> This one Text of Scripture, quite ſtrangles, and cuts the very throat-ſtrings, nerves, and finews of all thoſe counter-Arguments drawn, and taken from the examples of <hi>Henoch, Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Elias, Coloſſ:</hi> 1.18. ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Chriſt is the head of the body the Church: the beginning, the firſt borne from the dead, that in all things he might have the preeminence:</hi> which could not poſſibly be, if ever fleſh and blood entred into Heaven before him: and for this cauſe it is that the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls him <hi>our Captain,</hi> (or Leader) <hi>Heb:</hi> 2.10. <hi>And our fore-runner. Heb:</hi> 6.20. <hi>Whither the fore-runner
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40509:28"/>is for us entred, even Jeſus that is made an High Prieſt for ever after the order of Melchizedech.</hi> Deo Gloria.</p>
               <closer>In all this that I have here written I ſubmit to the ſounder, and ſincerer Judgement, and cenſure of my Mother the Orthodox Church of England.</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
